So, these are a few questions that I've gathered up.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have been celibate for some time and now have the fear that I will lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is full of fear and has no peace, yet peace is what I expected to get from celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I doing wrong?
[SPEAKER_02]: You get peace from losing desire towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't get peace for celibacy if you still value sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, celibacy is a necessary prerequisite to lose the desire towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't, eh... if you don't work on that part, mental part of your attraction to sensual objects, no, celibacy will free you and give you... well, it will give you certainly a less disturbing life, a less engaging life, less entanglement in life.
[SPEAKER_02]: Being... not engaging physically with sensuality is factually less entangling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, eh... yes, if you still value sensuality, value sensual objects, eh... saying no to them will hurt.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, did you, did that person expect celibacy to do the work for him, her?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if I'm celibate, if I just abstain from this, sensuality will magically evaporate from my mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or did they also, on top of that, sense restraint, virtue, celibacy, then make the effort to see the peril in sense objects, to see the peril in desire?
[SPEAKER_02]: If not, then the peace they were hoping to get on account of celibacy alone, it's kind of on the level of sensual satisfaction again.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were hoping that they will have this pleasure of a peaceful experience because they're not engaging sexually anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be too easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then we would say just be celibate and that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to be, if you want to be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in and of itself, it will not result in the unshakable peace.
[SPEAKER_02]: But factually, as I said, it will still result in less entanglements.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, focus on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ponder on the benefits of doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't just hope.
[SPEAKER_02]: That it will do the work for you, while you mentally still value the central objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once you celebrate, are you now spending your time contemplating the danger of sense desires, the lack of satisfaction, the context of, you know, entanglement and disentanglement, the value of disentanglement,
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you making the effort on that mental level now, that you created the basis through celibacy and virtue, or are you just celibate and then just sort of threading water, just waiting for the work to magically be presented as completed?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's similar to someone who is, like, just doing, taking on the rules, taking on certain precepts, and then hoping that... Yeah, okay, so I understand now my duty is to be celibate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, I'm celibate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, so, so where's the peace?
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't come as a result of it, because you haven't taken it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You take celibacy so that you can tame your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't take celibacy because that will do the work for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, remind yourself for reasons of wanting to practice, keep that context, work on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's again, it's a simile of lighting the sticks, eh, fire sticks, lighting the fire with the sticks, while you're in the water.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can then, you realize, I have to come out of this river, in order to sort of rub the sticks to get the fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just come out of the river and you make no effort to rub the sticks to light the fire, well, you won't get the fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: You still won't get the original result that made you come out of the water.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to come out of the water.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why celibacy is not optional for somebody who wants to practice really for the results.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, once you celibate, that's not the end of the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Coming out of the water, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, learning to light a fire and making the effort to dry the sticks, not soak them, not keep them in touch with water, even if you are out...
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, stop valuing sensuality, stop hoping for some degree of sensual pleasures after I become peaceful and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to say no to that entire domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you would say no, not by kind of, I'll just decide to say no, but by contemplating the factual danger of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The factual lack of satisfaction, the factual perpetuation of the problem and non-peace.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that, in and of itself, would be enough, actually, to already start seeing the benefits of being celibate, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the dangers of not.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the dangers of not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you don't get some higher results, you still recognize, well, yeah, it's still factually... More freedom comes that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a question that's related to this,
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that I'm old, celibacy is quite easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of my previous passions have faded and now I dwell, equanimous to most things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I fear that sickness and death will still be suffering for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: What should I do next?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think what should I do first is more likely what you should ask.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because celibacy and freedom from sensuality does not come with old age by default.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said before, it goes underground with old age, by default.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means you think now it's not there, because it's too far gone to see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the reminders of it still being there are, like, hard to spot.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, the vitality, the strength of the senses, the zeal, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just tired, jaded.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the attitude, the assumption of what... where the lust is, where the attraction is, where the desires are being satisfied, that's still there, and that's now much harder to see and uproot.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if... if the person then gets sick, if the person is truly equanimous, then losing... the prospect of losing the body, even more...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you truly practice celibacy to its fulfillment, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: abandoning of sensual desires,
[SPEAKER_02]: A prospect of sickness and death would not be frightening at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you would not even be doubtful about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that, which is going to be wiped away with sickness and death, is that which you seemingly have no desire towards anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So now your senses, that you're still very much bound with, are even more invisible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Remember we spoke in previous talk, senses... sense organs are always like negative.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're the negative space in regard to what you look, see, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it is defined in return by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is how you can infer and discern that organs are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, when sight, smell, taste, touches have been
[SPEAKER_02]: Bombarding you for decades and decades and decades and fatigue and you have no more inspiration or strength and like joy towards the pleasures.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just tired.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'd just rather not be bothered.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means your negative spaces of your senses will be even more invisible now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're factually not being as defined as before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what people confuse as peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look, I'm not disturbed as much as I was before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you're getting old.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you truly want to see if you're peaceful or not, well, contemplate losing the dear ones, the loved ones, experiencing misfortune.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can you still experience things on account of anything that could happen to this body?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sickness, aging, perils of that kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would you equally remain unperturbed if you live or die in the next moment?
[SPEAKER_02]: If not, means... okay, so, you missed the opportunity to uproot the dependence on the negative sense organs, negative spaces of the sense organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, now it's going to be even harder.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I guess what you could do is, again, spend every minute of your life contemplating the value of virtue, sensory strength, practice generosity, don't give rise to thoughts of ill-will, thoughts of harm,
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't give rise to the sense of false complacency and safety on account of things not disturbing you much.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if you were truly free, you have nothing to lose with all these practices.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you were not rooted free, well, you'll realize soon enough, with all these practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because also eating, a person could take on certain... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplate the reasons for the eating.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The practice increased moderation in eating, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's still something that people will rarely get into.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is something we derive pleasure from, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't have this sexual part anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure, but sounds, touches, food, comfort, physical comfort, being sheltered from the elements.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I don't mean like, you know, go and live outside blizzard or something, but how soft is your bed?
[SPEAKER_02]: How soft are your pillows?
[SPEAKER_02]: How warm are your blankets?
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that, the purpose is one and only, just to provide comfort for the body, for the sense organs that you still are.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, would you be disturbed on account of losing those things, on account of maybe saying no, to a degree, and sleep on a harder bed, without a pillow?
[SPEAKER_02]: How miserable you'll be next day, if you even didn't have a proper night of comfortable sleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can still practice within that, even if you waited.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, there was that old lady, old, like, past eighty or whatever, in the suttas, that was... had, what, I think, two sons, husband, lots of wealth, husband passed away.
[SPEAKER_02]: She thought, hey, why don't I give my wealth to my two sons and their families, and they'll look after me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So she gave all of her wealth, house, everything to the two sons, and then from, you know, she would spend time with one, then go and spend time with the other, and on one occasion, when she was like that, arriving at one son's house, before she could... she overheard him saying, oh, there she is coming again, like, well, she has the other son, doesn't she?
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, the wife complaining or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So she was heartbroken, the fact that they actually started despising her.
[SPEAKER_02]: When she factually gave it all away.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he left.
[SPEAKER_02]: She left.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saw the nuns getting shelter in the food and thought, well, I might as well become a nun, so I can at least have somewhere to sleep and eat.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, she didn't even want to practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: She was old.
[SPEAKER_02]: She couldn't go Pindapad, because she was old.
[SPEAKER_02]: She was just... would clean up the place when the younger nuns go for Pindapad, prepare everything, when they bring the food.
[SPEAKER_02]: She was just like a servant there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And once she overheard one nun talk to the other about the
[SPEAKER_02]: Some aspect of the dhamma that they heard from the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, at night, when she finished all of her chores, she couldn't even do the walking meditation straight, because she was so old.
[SPEAKER_02]: She was walking up and down the corridor, propped with... against the wall, and contemplating what she heard.
[SPEAKER_02]: And she became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it is still possible, but you do really have to commit to it, like it is your last chance, because it might well be, for a long, long time.